Hey everyone, Grant here. This is the
first video in a series on the essence
of calculus, and I'll be publishing the
following videos once per day for the
next 10 days.
The goal here, as the name suggests, is
to really get the heart of the subject
out in one binge-watchable set. But with
a topic that's as broad as calculus,
there's a lot of things that can mean.
So, here's what I have in mind
specifically.
Calculus has a lot of rules and
formulas, which are often presented as
things to be memorized. Lots of
derivative formulas, the product rule,
the chain rule, implicit
differentiation, the fact that integrals
and derivatives are opposite, Taylor
series, just a lot of things like that.
And my goal is for you to come away
feeling like you could have invented
calculus yourself.
That is, cover all those core ideas, but
in a way that makes clear where they
actually come from and what they really
mean, using an all-around visual
approach.
Inventing math is no joke, and there is
a difference between being told why
something's true and actually generating
it from scratch. But at all points, I
want you to think to yourself, if you
were an early mathematician pondering
these ideas and drawing out the right
diagrams, does it feel reasonable that
you could have stumbled across these
truths yourself?
In this initial video, I want to show
how you might stumble into the core
ideas of calculus by thinking very
deeply about one specific bit of
geometry, the area of a circle.
Maybe you know that this is pi times its
radius squared, but why? Is there a nice
way to think about where this formula
comes from?
Well, contemplating this problem and
leaving yourself open to exploring the
interesting thoughts that come about can
actually lead you to a glimpse of three
big ideas in calculus, integrals,
derivatives, and the fact that they're
opposites.
But the story starts more simply, just
you and a circle. Let's say with radius
three.
You're trying to figure out its area,
and after going through a lot of paper
trying different ways to chop up and
rearrange the pieces of that area, many
of which might lead to their own
interesting observations, maybe you try
out the idea of slicing up the circle
into many concentric rings.
This should seem promising because it
respects the symmetry of the circle, and
math has a tendency to reward you when
you respect its symmetries.
Let's take one of those rings, which has
some inner radius r that's between zero
and three.
If we can find a nice expression for the
area of each ring like this one, and if
we have a nice way to add them all up,
it might lead us to an understanding of
the full circle's area.
Maybe you start by imagining
straightening out this ring.
And you could try thinking through
exactly what this new shape is and what
its area should be, but for simplicity,
let's just approximate it as a
rectangle.
The width of that rectangle is the
circumference of the original ring,
which is 2 pi * r, right? I mean, that's
essentially the definition of pi.
And its thickness?
Well, that depends on how finely you
chopped up the circle in the first
place, which was kind of arbitrary.
In the spirit of using what will come to
be standard calculus notation, let's
call that thickness dr for a tiny
difference in the radius from one ring
to the next. Maybe you think of it as
something like 0.1.
So, approximating this unwrapped ring as
a thin rectangle, its area is 2 pi * r,
the radius, * dr, the little thickness.
And even though that's not perfect, for
smaller and smaller choices of dr, this
is actually going to be a better and
better approximation for that area,
since the top and the bottom sides of
this shape are going to get closer and
closer to being exactly the same length.
So, let's just move forward with this
approximation, keeping in the back of
our minds that it's slightly wrong, but
it's going to become more accurate for
smaller and smaller choices of dr.
That is, if we slice up the circle into
thinner and thinner rings.
So, just to sum up where we are, you've
broken up the area of the circle into
all of these rings, and you're
approximating the area of each one of
those as 2 pi times its radius times dr.
Where the specific value for that inner
radius ranges from zero for the smallest
ring up to just under three for the
biggest ring, spaced out by whatever the
thickness is that you choose for dr,
something like 0.1.
And notice that the spacing between the
values here corresponds to the thickness
dr of each ring, the difference in
radius from one ring to the next.
In fact, a nice way to think about the
rectangles approximating each ring's
area is to fit them all upright side by
side along this axis.
Each one has a thickness dr, which is
why they fit so snugly right there
together, and the height of any one of
these rectangles sitting above some
specific value of r, like 0.6, is
exactly 2 pi times that value.
That's the circumference of the
corresponding ring that this rectangle
approximates.
Pictures like this 2 pi r can actually
get kind of tall for the screen. I mean,
2 * pi * 3 is around 19, so let's just
throw up a y axis that's scaled a little
differently so that we can actually fit
all of these rectangles on the screen.
A nice way to think about this setup is
to draw the graph of 2 pi r, which is a
straight line that has a slope 2 pi.
Each of these rectangles extends up to
the point where it just barely touches
that graph.
Again, we're being approximate here.
Each of these rectangles only
approximates the area of the
corresponding ring from the circle.
But remember, that approximation, 2 pi r
times dr,
gets less and less wrong as the size of
dr gets smaller and smaller.
And this has a very beautiful meaning
when we're looking at the sum of the
areas of all those rectangles.
For smaller and smaller choices of dr,
you might at first think that that turns
the problem into a monstrously large
sum. I mean, there's many many
rectangles to consider and the decimal
precision of each one of their areas is
going to be an absolute nightmare.
But notice, all of their areas in
aggregate just looks like the area under
a graph.
And that portion under the graph is just
a triangle. A triangle with a base of
three and a height that's 2π * 3.
So, its area, 1/2 base * height, works
out to be exactly
π * 3 squared.
Or if the radius of our original circle
was some other value, capital R, that
area comes out to be π * R squared.
And that's the formula for the area of a
circle.
It doesn't matter who you are or what
you typically think of math, that right
there is a beautiful argument.
But if you want to think like a
mathematician here, you don't just care
about finding the answer. You care about
developing general problem-solving tools
and techniques.
So, take a moment to meditate on what
exactly just happened and why it worked.
Cuz the way that we transitioned from
something approximate to something
precise is actually pretty subtle and it
cuts deep to what calculus is all about.
You had this problem that could be
approximated with the sum of many small
numbers, each of which looked like 2πr *
dr for values of r ranging between 0 and
3.
Remember, the small number dr here
represents our choice for the thickness
of each ring, for example, 0.1.
And there are two important things to
note here.
First of all, not only is dr a factor in
the quantities we're adding up, 2πr *
dr,
it also gives the spacing between the
different values of r.
And secondly, the smaller our choice for
dr, the better the approximation.
Adding all of those numbers could be
seen in a different, pretty clever way
as adding the areas of many thin
rectangles sitting underneath the graph,
the graph of the function 2πr in this
case.
Then, and this is key, by considering
smaller and smaller choices for dr,
corresponding to better and better
approximations of the original problem,
the sum, thought of as the aggregate
area of those rectangles, approaches the
area under the graph.
And because of that, you can conclude
that the answer to the original
question, in full unapproximated
precision, is exactly the same as the
area underneath this graph.
A lot of other hard problems in math and
science can be broken down and
approximated as the sum of many small
quantities. Things like figuring out how
far a car has traveled based on its
velocity at each point in time.
In a case like that, you might range
through many different points in time,
and at each one multiply the velocity at
that time times a tiny change in time,
dt, which would give the corresponding
little bit of distance traveled during
that little time.
I'll talk through the details of
examples like this later in the series,
but at a high level, many of these types
of problems turn out to be equivalent to
finding the area under some graph, in
much the same way that our circle
problem did.
This happens whenever the quantities
that you're adding up, the one whose sum
approximates the original problem, can
be thought of as the areas of many thin
rectangles sitting side by side like
this.
If finer and finer approximations of the
original problem correspond to thinner
and thinner rings,
then the original problem is going to be
equivalent to finding the area under
some graph.
Again, this is an idea we'll see in more
detail later in the series, so don't
worry if it's not 100% clear right now.
The point now is that you, as the
mathematician having just solved a
problem by reframing it as the area
under a graph,
might start thinking about how to find
the areas under other graphs.
I mean, we were lucky in the circle
problem that the relevant area turned
out to be a triangle, but imagine
instead something like a parabola, the
graph of x squared.
What's the area underneath that curve,
say between the values of x = 0 and x =
3?
Well, it's hard to think about, right?
And let me reframe that question in a
slightly different way.
We'll fix that left end point in place
at zero, and let the right end point
vary.
Are you able to find a function A of X
that gives you the area under this
parabola between zero and X?
A function A of X like this is called an
integral of X squared.
Calculus holds within it the tools to
figure out what an integral like this
is, but right now, it's just a mystery
function to us. We know it gives the
area under the graph of X squared
between some fixed left point and some
variable right point, but we don't know
what it is.
And again, the reason we care about this
kind of question is not just for the
sake of asking hard geometry questions,
it's because many practical problems
that can be approximated by adding up a
large number of small things can be
reframed as a question about an area
under a certain graph.
And I'll tell you right now that finding
this area, this integral function, is
genuinely hard.
And whenever you come across a genuinely
hard question in math, a good policy is
to not try too hard to get at the answer
directly, since usually you just end up
banging your head against a wall.
Instead, play around with the idea with
no particular goal in mind. Spend some
time building up familiarity with the
interplay between the function defining
the graph, in this case x squared, and
the function giving the area.
In that playful spirit, if you're lucky,
here's something that you might notice.
When you slightly increase x by some
tiny nudge, dx,
look at the resulting change in area,
represented with this sliver that I'm
going to call dA, for a tiny difference
in area.
That sliver can be pretty well
approximated with a rectangle, one whose
height is x squared, and whose width is
dx.
And the smaller the size of that nudge,
dx, the more that sliver actually looks
like a rectangle.
Now, this gives us an interesting way to
think about how A of x is related to x
squared.
A change to the output of A, this little
dA, is about equal to x squared, where x
is whatever input you started at, times
dx, the little nudge to the input that
caused A to change.
Or rearranged, dA divided by dx, the
ratio of a tiny change in A to the tiny
change in x that caused it, is
approximately whatever x squared is at
that point.
And that's an approximation that should
get better and better for smaller and
smaller choices of dx.
In other words, we don't know what A of
x is. That remains a mystery. But, we do
know a property that this mystery
function must have.
When you look at two nearby points, for
example, 3 and 3.001,
consider the change to the output of A
between those two points. The difference
between the mystery function evaluated
at 3.001
and evaluated at 3.
That change divided by the difference in
the input values, which in this case is
0.001,
should be about equal to the value of x
squared for the starting input, in this
case, 3 squared.
And this relationship between tiny
changes to the mystery function and the
values of x squared itself is true at
all inputs, not just three.
That doesn't immediately tell us how to
find A of X, but it provides a very
strong clue that we can work with.
And there's nothing special about the
graph x squared here. Any function
defined as the area under some graph has
this property that dA divided by dx, a
slight nudge to the output of A divided
by a slight nudge to the input that
caused it,
is about equal to the height of the
graph at that point.
Again, that's an approximation that gets
better and better for smaller choices of
dx.
And here, we're stumbling into another
big idea from calculus, derivatives.
This ratio dA divided by dx is called
the derivative of A,
or more technically, the derivative is
whatever this ratio approaches as dx
gets smaller and smaller.
I'll dive much more deeply into the idea
of a derivative in the next video, but
loosely speaking, it's a measure of how
sensitive a function is to small changes
in its input.
You'll see as the series goes on that
there are many, many ways that you can
visualize a derivative, depending on
what function you're looking at and how
you think about tiny nudges to its
output.
And we care about derivatives because
they help us solve problems. And in our
little exploration here, we already have
a slight glimpse of one way that they're
used.
They are the key to solving integral
questions, problems that require finding
the area under a curve.
Once you gain enough familiarity with
computing derivatives, you'll be able to
look at a situation like this one where
you don't know what a function is, but
you do know that its derivative should
be x squared,
and from that, reverse engineer what the
function must be.
And this back and forth between
and derivatives, where the derivative of
a function for the area under a graph
gives you back the function defining the
graph itself,
is called the fundamental theorem of
calculus.
It ties together the two big ideas of
integrals and derivatives.
And it shows how, in some sense, each
one is an inverse of the other.
All of this is only a high-level view,
just a peek at some of the core ideas
that emerge in calculus. And what
follows in the series are the details
for derivatives and integrals and more.
At all points, I want you to feel that
you could have invented calculus
yourself.
That if you drew the right pictures and
played with each idea in just the right
way,
these formulas and rules and constructs
that are presented could have just as
easily popped out naturally from your
own explorations.
And before you go, it would feel wrong
not to give the people who supported
this series on Patreon a well-deserved
thanks, both for their financial backing
as well as for the suggestions they gave
while the series was being developed.
You see, supporters got early access to
the videos as I made them, and they'll
continue to get early access for future
Essence of type series.
And as a thanks to the community, I keep
ads off of new videos for their first
month.
I'm still astounded that I can spend
time working on videos like these, and
in a very direct way, you are the one to
thank for that.